Finding Aid for Alexander Eckstein Papers 1943-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alexander Eckstein Papers 1943-1976
Eckstein, Alexander, 1915-
Professor of economics and director of the Center for Chinese Studies at the University of Michigan, and consultant on China to the U. S. Department of State. China files relating to the Chinese economy and to the reopening of relations with the Peoples Republic of China; also correspondence and talk files; papers and photographs relating to professional travels; writings; and miscellaneous University and Vietnam subject files.
85149 Aa 2
10.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Ruth Eckstein (donor no. 6915 ), May 5, 1983.
The collection is open for research.
Alexander Eckstein, born December 9, 1915 in Novisad, Yugoslavia, came to the United States as a student in 1936. In 1939, he received his B. S. from the University of California at Berkeley in plant science. He continued his graduate work at Berkeley, studying agricultural economics, and earning his M. S. in 1941 and his Ph.D. in 1952.
On December 6, 1943 Alexander Eckstein became a naturalized citizen of the United States. He served overseas in the U. S. Army from 1943 to 1946, interrogating German prisoners and analyzing captured documents. After the War, Eckstein married Ruth Rubinstein (February 21, 1947).
From 1946 until 1949, Eckstein worked as an economist for the Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations. At the same time, he worked on finishing his dissertation, "The Economic Development of Hungary, 1920 to 1950: A Study in the Growth of an Economically Underdeveloped Area." During 1949-1950, he was appointed Area Research Fellow for the Social Science Research Council, and from 1951-1953, he worked as a senior economist for the Department of State.
In 1953, Eckstein was a lecturer and research associate at Harvard's Russian Research Center. Though he then specialized in comparative economic studies of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, Eckstein was also becoming increasingly involved in Chinese studies in 1956, be became a lecturer and research associate in the Department of Economics at Harvard, while he plunged into studying China and the Chinese economy. In 1959 he went to Formosa (Taiwan) to Put the finishing touches on his command of the Chinese language.
Upon his return to the United States, Eckstein was named the Haloid-Xerox Professor of International Economics at the University of Rochester. He taught in this position until 1961, when he came to the University of Michigan as a Professor of Economics. He remained at the University of Michigan until his death in 1976. During this period, Eckstein was simultaneously a consultant to the Department of State (1962-1976), Director of the Center for Chinese Studies (1967-1969) and Director of the Chinese Economic Studies project (1975-1976).
Eckstein included among his professional and honorary society memberships the American Economic Association, the Association for Asian Studies (Director, 1961/62 - 1963/64; Program Chairman, 1964; Member of Executive Group, Committee on American Library Resources on the Far East, 1963-1964), the Association for Comparative Economics, the Council on Foreign Relations, the Economic History Association and the Economic History Society. He was also active in a number of national organizations, most notably the National Committee on United States-China Relations (NCUSCR). From 1966 to 1976 he was a member and a Board member of the Executive Committee of the NCUSCR. He was Vice-Chairman of the Board of Directors, in 1968-1969, and Chairman from 1970 to 1972. Eckstein was on the Editorial Board of the magazines World Politics and The China Quarterly. He was a member of the Academic Advisory Board for the National Council for United States-China Trade.
During the last ten years of his life, Eckstein was a part of the Committee on Scholarly Exchanges with the People's Republic of China. For the Social Science Research Council, he served with the Joint Committee for the Study of Contemporary China (also sponsored by the American Council of Learned Societies), 1959-1966, and the Committee on the Economy of china, 1961-1969. His other affiliations included the Visiting Committees for the Brookings Institution and Harvard University, the International Committee for Chinese Studies, the Association for the Study of Soviet-Type Economies, and the Association for Comparative Economic Studies (of which he was the President in 1974).
In addition to this multitude of professional activity, Eckstein was a prolific author. His own books include The National Income of China (1961), Communist China's Economic Growth and Foreign Trade (1966), China's Economic Development: The Interplay of Scarcity and Ideology (1975), and China's Economic Revolution (1977, published posthumously). He co-authored two books - Prospects for Communist China (1954, with W. W. Hatch, J. R. Kierman, and W. W. Rostow) and Moscow-Peking Axis (1957, with Boorman, Mosely and Schwartz). He was the editor of Economic Trends in Communist China (1968, with Walter Galenson and T. C. Liu), Comparison of Economic Systems: Theoretical and Methodological Approaches (1971), China Trade Prospects and U. S. Policy (1971) and Quantitative Measures of China's Economic Output (1980, published posthumously). He also wrote numerous articles.
Since he believed that Communist China would become a permanent and powerful nation-state on the world scene, Eckstein was an advocate of initiating more cordial relations with the People's Republic of China from an early date. Through his involvement in the NCUSCR, Eckstein played an important role in arranging the visit of the Chinese Table Tennis Team which cleared the way for Henry Kissinger and Richard Nixon's historic flights to Peking in 1972. Once the first contact had been established, he continued to work for expanded exchanges between the United States and China, not only in athletics, but also in trade, and scholarly and cultural matters.
Having witnessed the disruption of Chinese studies in the United States during the McCarthy era, Eckstein was concerned about educating a new generation of China scholars. This was the motivation behind his interest in the establishment and maintenance of centers for Chinese research, not only at the University of Michigan but at other universities as well.
His work on China led Eckstein to take a public stand on the Vietnam War. Although he was by no means a dove, he was an outspoken critic of President Johnson's Vietnam policy. Together with several other Michigan professors, many of them also in the China field, Eckstein began a study group on Vietnam. On several occasions he gave testimony before different Congressional committees, and from 1966-1968, he was a member of the State Department Advisory Panel on China.
As a public-spirited man, Eckstein was an active campaigner for Donald M. Riegle and Presidential candidate Robert F. Kennedy. He took an interest in the case of Robert Williams, a Black activist accused of kidnapping a White couple. And within the University, he served as a member of the Faculty Reform Coalition, which was primarily concerned with the quality of education received by minority students at Michigan.
Alexander Eckstein died of a heart attack at age sixty-one on December 5, 1976. Through his work, both academic and political, he was an influential force behind the improved relations between the United States and the People's Republic of China, and was a significant figure in furthering the study of China in this country.
The papers of Alexander Eckstein consist of 10.3 linear feet of material. The collection most heavily documents the last twenty-five years of Eckstein's life, roughly the years 1960-1976, although there is some earlier material dating back to World War II. The papers deal almost exclusively with his professional life; there is very little of a personal nature included. Furthermore, the bulk of the collection concerns primarily his work and interest in China, although the section of his writings does contain material on Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union. The papers portray Eckstein the scholar rather than Eckstein the professor. For instance there are no materials relating to his term as Director of the China Center at the University of Michigan or to the Chinese Economic Studies project which he directed. The collection is divided into the following major series: Personal, China, Personal Correspondence, Talks, Trips, University of Michigan, Vietnam, Writings, Sound Recordings, and Photographs.
Subjects:
China--History--1949-1976.; Commerce.; Eckstein, Alexander, 1915-1976; Economics.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; United States. Dept. of State.; United States--Foreign relations--China.
Subjects - Visual Material:
United States--Foreign relations--China.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal
  Personal contains biographical materials, memorabilia from World War II, newspaper clippings about Eckstein, obituaries, eulogies and other materials relating to Eckstein personally.
  - Biographical Materials (Box 1)
  - Federal Employment Forms (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia (World War II) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1976 (Box 1)
  - Eulogies (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of Condolence (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
- China
  The section China is the largest series within the collection. Here Eckstein filed the records documenting his involvement with China-related organizations (notably NCUSCR and the SSRC). In addition, this series includes files relating to the opening of relations with China -- Congressional testimony, statements on U. S. - China policy, and papers pertaining to various conferences and seminars. Eckstein's role in the opening of relations with the People's Republic of China will be of interest to the student of Chinese and American diplomacy, or political science. Furthermore, anyone interested in the role of American "China Watchers" or more generally in the influence of academics upon government policy will find these papers helpful. Regarding China specifically, most of Eckstein's work on the Chinese economy has been published. The collection does contain, however, substantial amounts of data collected by him. Of particular note is the computer printout "Commodity Composite of the Foreign Trade of the People's Republic of China with the Free World and the USSR, 1955 - 1973," (box 11).
  - Association for Asian Studies (Box 1)
  - China Advisory Panel, State Department
    - Correspondence 1961-1967 (Box 1)
    - Program May 22, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Research Materials (including AE Study for State Department) (Box 1)
    - Research Memoranda 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - "Themes to be Examined" (by the Panel) 1966 (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Citizen Exchange Corps 1970 (Box 1)
  - Collected Materials, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee for Economic Development (CED)
    - Draft Policy Statement 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Policy Statement on East-West Trade 1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (CSCPRC)
    - Correspondence
      - 1973-April 21, 1975 (Box 1)
      - April 23, 1975-May 1975 (Box 1)
      - July 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Meetings 1969-1976 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda
      - 1973-October 1975 (Box 1)
      - November 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Papers
      - 1973-June 1975 (Box 2)
      - July 1975-April 1976 (Box 2)
      - May 1976 (Box 2)
    - Programs (Box 2)
    - Proposals
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - "Commodity Composite of the Foreign Trade of the People's Republic of China with the Free World and the USSR, 1955-1973" (Box 11)
  - Congressional Testimony
    - Correspondence 1966-1976 (Box 2)
    - Statements
      - Drafts, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Printed Statements
        - House Committee on International Relations 1976 (Box 2)
        - House Subcommittee on Asian and Pacific Affairs
          - 1966 (Box 2)
          - 1970 (Box 2)
        - House Subcommittee on the Far East and the Pacific 1966 (Box 2)
        - Joint Economic Committee
          - 1957 (Box 2)
          - 1967 (Box 2)
          - 1978 (Box 2)
          - Subcommittee on Foreign Economic Policy 1956 (Box 2)
        - Senate Committee on Foreign Relations
          - Hearings 1966 (Box 2)
          - China, Vietnam and the United States 1966 (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Consultant to State Department (AE appointment) (Box 2)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Box 2)
  - CTP Interview Notes 1970-1975, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Democratic Advisory Council
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Statements (Box 3)
  - Democratic Study Group on Asia
    - Notes (by AE) (Box 3)
    - Papers (Box 3)
    - Reprints (Box 3)
    - Statement of Purpose (Box 3)
  - Exchanges with the PRC 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Joint Committee on Contemporary China (JCCC. Social Science Research Council and American Council of Learned Societies)
    - Conferences 1959-1967 (Box 3)
    - History of JCCC 1971 (Box 3)
    - Meetings
      - 1959-1961 (Box 3)
      - 1964-1971 (Box 3)
    - Policies and Proposals
      - 1960-1969 (Box 3)
      - "The Development of Chinese Studies in the 1970s Options and Recommendations" by Michel Oksenberg (Box 3)
    - Research Materials, problems with
      - 1961-1966 (Box 3)
      - "A Report on the Availability..." by Eugene Wu, for the Subcommittee on Materials (Box 3)
    - Survey of Graduate Students 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - National Committee on U.S.-China Relations (NCUSCR)
    - Annual Reports 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Budget. 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Conferences 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Exchanges with the PRC
      - General
        - 1972-1974 (Box 3)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Athletic Exchanges
        - Table Tennis (Ping-pong)
          - General (Box 3)
          - Chinese Delegation (Box 3)
          - Funding
            - 1971 (Box 3)
            - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
          - History of Table Tennis Exchange (Box 3)
          - Itineraries, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - Newspaper Clippings
            - 1971-April 15, 1972 (Box 3)
            - April 16, 1972-August 1972 (Box 3)
          - Planning
            - to July, 1971 (Box 3)
            - August 1971-June 1972 (Box 3)
          - Publicity (Box 4)
          - Souvenirs (Box 4)
          - Miscellanea (Box 4)
      - Cultural Exchanges
        - 1971-1973 (Box 4)
        - 1974 (Chinese Archaeological Exhibition) (Box 4)
      - Scholarly Exchanges 1965-1975 (Box 4)
      - Trade Exchanges 1970-1976 (Box 4)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors 1974-1976 (Box 4)
      - Executive Committee 1972-1975 (Box 4)
      - Others 1974-1976 (Box 4)
    - Membership 1974-1976 (Box 4)
    - National Council for U.S.-China Trade 1973-1975 (Box 4)
    - Organization 1971-1976 (Box 4)
    - Policies and Programs
      - 1971-1974 (Box 4)
      - 1975 (Box 4)
    - Proposal for the Establishment of a China Trade Information Service 1971-1973 (Box 4)
    - Publications 1968-1972 (including reviews) (Box 4)
    - Trade Study Group
      - Undated (Box 4)
      - 1968 (Box 4)
      - January-April 1969 (Box 4)
      - May-November 1969 (Box 4)
      - December 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1954-1976 (Box 4)
  - Notes
    - China, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Sino-Soviet Economic Relations (Box 4)
  - Research, State of
    - 1960-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Twentieth International Congress of Chinese Studies, Prague 1968 (Box 5)
    - 1967-1976 (Box 5)
  - Seminars
    - National Seminar on Communist China November 19-21, 1965 (Box 5)
    - National War College February 1971 (Box 5)
    - Seminar on Sino-Soviet Relations, Harvard February 1961 (Box 5)
  - Social Science Research Council (SSRC)
    - Area Studies Committee, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Committee on the Economics of China
      - General 1962-1971 (Box 5)
      - Meetings 1960-1969 (Box 5)
      - Study Economic Trends in Communist China
        - Correspondence 1961-1969, 4 folders (Box 5)
        - Criticisms 1965-1969 (Box 5)
        - Drafts
          - Chang, John K. "Industrial Development of Mainland China, 1912-1949" (Box 5)
          - Chang, Perry P. "The Theory and Practice of Monetary Control in Communist China" (Box 5)
          - Eckstein, Alexander. "The Economic Heritage" (Box 5)
          - Eckstein, Alexander with Walter Galenson and Ta-Chang Liu. "Introduction" (Box 5)
          - Field, Robert Michael. "Labor Productivity in Industry During the First Five Year Plan" (Box 5)
          - Mah, Feng-hwa. "The Foreign Trade of Communist China!" (Box 5)
          - Tang, Anthony M. "Policy and Performance in Agriculture" (Box 5)
          - Walker, Kenneth R. "Organization for Agricultural Production in China" (Box 5)
        - Materials (Box 5)
        - Outlines (Box 5)
        - Pilot Study (by Helen Yin) (Box 5)
        - Proposals
          - Undated (Box 5)
          - 1962-1969 (Box 5)
        - Resumes (Box 5)
        - Miscellanea (Box 5)
    - Committee on Exchanges with Asian Institutions 1971 (Box 6)
    - Conferences 1967-1971 (Box 6)
    - Grants
      - Applications (Box 6)
      - Information (Box 6)
    - Items-SSRC magazine, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - Liaison Committee 1965-1971 (Box 6)
    - Study: C.S. Chen-"The Mineral Resources and Industrial Capabilities of Manchuria" (Box 6)
    - Study: Alexander Eckstein and John Chang-"Economic Growth in Manchuria 1920-1960: A Case Study in the Expansion of an Undeveloped Frontier Under Colonial Auspices" (Box 6)
  - Trade Conferences
    - University of Chicago 1967 (Box 6)
    - Others 1971 (Box 6)
  - U.S. China Policy, statements 1966-1976, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea (Box 6)
- Personal Correspondence File 1960-1976
  Eckstein arranged his Personal Correspondence alphabetically. The names of some of his correspondents include several top American-Chins, scholars, such as Doak Barnett, John King Fairbank, Edgar Snow, and Allen Whiting. There is also a file for Henry Kissinger. These files also contain non-correspondence, such as clippings or reprints. In addition, the researcher should note the filing of correspondence throughout the China series, especially under the names of organizations.
  - Barnett, Doak A. (Box 6)
  - Chang, John (Box 6)
  - Chao, Kang (Box 6)
  - Chen, Pi-chao (Peter) (Box 6)
  - Cheng, Chu-yuan (Box 6)
  - Fairbank, John King (Box 6)
  - Hua, Huang (Box 6)
  - Julius, Steve (Box 6)
  - Kennedy, Edward and Robert (Box 6)
  - Kirschen, E.S. (Box 6)
  - Kissinger, Henry (Box 6)
  - Kobler, Franz (Box 6)
  - KorkoreffAlexander (Box 6)
  - Laird, Melvin R. (Box 6)
  - Lindbeck, John (Box 6)
  - Little, Arthur D. (Box 6)
  - Lockwood, William F. (Box 6)
  - Pleng, Ming-Min (Box 6)
  - Riegle, Donald W. (Box 6)
  - Reynolds, Bruce (Box 6)
  - Robinson, Dana I. (Box 6)
  - Rubin, Vitali A. (Box 6)
  - Snow, Edgar (Box 6)
  - Stewart, Sir Michael (Box 6)
  - Sweitzer, James (Box 6)
  - Tuan, Chi-hsien (Box 6)
  - Vivian, Weston (Box 6)
  - Vogel, Ezra (Box 6)
  - Walker, Kenneth R. (Box 6)
  - Walker, Richard L. (Box 6)
  - Wegman, Myron E. (Box 6)
  - Whiting, Allen (Box 6)
  - Williams, Robert (Box 6)
  - Wu, Jack (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea 1955-1976 (Box 6)
- Talks
  Talks includes a small section of radio broadcasts and a larger series consisting of notes for talks given on a variety of foreign affairs topics. These files have been arranged alphabetically and cover the period 1955-1971.
  - "China's Developing Trade and the World Economy," 1969 (Box 7)
  - "Communist Chinese Economic Development: Trends and Prospects" (Box 7)
  - "Comparative Development Patterns in India and China," 1966 (Box 7)
  - "Comparative Patterns of Economic Development of China and the Soviet Union," 1968 (Box 7)
  - "The Cultural and Economic Setting of Economic Rationality in Western and Eastern Europe" (Box 7)
  - "The Cultural Revolution: An Overview" (Box 7)
  - "The Cultural Revolution and its Policy Implications for the United States," 1968 (Box 7)
  - "The Economic Potential of the USSR for War," 1955 (Box 7)
  - "Individualism and the Role of the State in Economic Growth" (Box 7)
  - "Knowledge, Information and Innovation in the Soviet Economy" (Box 7)
  - "Problems in Economic Development Theory" (Box 7)
  - "Some Reflections on Economic Trends in China" (Box 7)
  - Summary of untitled speech 1955 (Box 7)
  - Talks and Lecture Notes on China (Box 7)
  - Radio Broadcasts
    - "China and the Triangular Power Game," July 28, 1971 (Box 7)
    - "Economic Development in Communist China," November 6, 1962 (Box 7)
- Trips
  Eckstein took a number of trips during his career. These were primarily research-oriented rather than for pleasure. His notes from these trips contain economic data collected during his visits. The Trips series also includes material concerning Eckstein's planning for the trips, correspondence with government officials and academics, schedules for speeches Eckstein would give while abroad, tours of industrial sites and meetings with representatives of economic agencies. Most of Eckstein's trips were to the Far East, but he also visited Australia, India, and Yugoslavia. Since his data was gathered first-hand, this section could be of use to anyone interested in the economies of the countries he toured.
  - Asia 1969 (Japan and Taiwan)
    - Address before Asian Affairs Research Council, Tokyo (Box 7)
    - Collected Materials (Box 7)
    - Contacts and Itineraries (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Notes, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Australia 1975
    - Australian National University Conference Notes (Box 7)
    - Contacts and Itineraries (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Impressions (Box 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 7)
  - China 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    series of note pads, plus final copy of notes
  - Hong Kong 1959 (Box 7)
  - India 1966
    - Contacts and Itineraries (Box 7)
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - State Department Travel Kit (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Japan 1959
    - Taiwan (Republic of China) 1959 (Box 7)
    - Notes, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Proposal for the Development of the Social Sciences and Humanities in Taiwan (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavia 1966
    - General (Box 7)
    - Yugoslav Institute for Economic Research 1968
      - Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Notes (Box 7)
      - Proposal (Box 7)
      - Questionnaire (Box 7)
      - Report (Box 7)
      - Miscellanea (Box 7)
- University of Michigan
  The section on the University of Michigan is somewhat disappointing, since it does not reflect many of Eckstein's activities at that institution. One very obvious lack is the complete absence of any material relating to his work as the Director of the China Center. Most of this section is concerned with Eckstein's part in the Faculty Reform Coalition (1970-1971), particularly the Council on Minority Affairs, the Opportunity Program and the University Judiciary. There are also files concerning the Walgreen Chair appointment, the Chabad House Project, University news releases, letters of recommendation, and various other matters. Most of the material covers the time span 1965-1971.
  - Chabad. House Project (Box 7)
  - Department of Economics
    - Communications with chairman, Peter O. Steiner 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    - Letters of recommendation 1966-1967 (Box 7)
    - Walgreen Chair 1968 (Box 7)
    - Miscellanea 1965-1976 (Box 7)